Greetings, and welcome to LGR Oddware,
大家好，欢迎收看LGR志异
where we're taking a look at hardware and software that is odd, forgotten, and obsolete,
在这里，我们将回顾一些怪异的，被遗忘的怪异软硬件
like this thing here, the Yamaha DiscT@2ing system,
诸如这个雅马哈的 DiscT@2ing CD刻录机
注：Tattoo指纹身，Bart由于纹身把他们家为圣诞存下来的钱都花光了:-(
@音同at，2音同tu，连一块T@2就发Tattoo的音
or rather the drive that allowed it to happen in the early 2000s.
一个只有在新千年的时候才会出现的奇葩玩意
And yeah it's kind of just a CD-RW,
没错，这就是一个CD刻录光驱
but its whole gimmick was the fact that you could burn,
不过这机器有个绝活，你可以在CD上直接纹上图案
or ink, "tattoos" directly onto your CD-R media,
not the label side, the data side.
不是在标签面哦，而是数据面
Let's check it out.
咱来看看吧
All right, so let's take a closer look at the Yamaha CRW-F1,
好的，现在我们来看看这个光驱，型号CRW-F1
or more precisely the external SCSI version known as the F1SX.
有一个更加稀有的外置SCSI接口版，型号F1SX
Yamaha made multiple models, external and internal,
雅马哈生产了很多种型号，有内置的，有外置的
many of which cost less than this one,
大多数都要比这个便宜
but they all had the DiscT@2 laser labeling system built in.
但是他们都内置了DiscT@2功能
"Draw images on your discs." Mmm~
“在光盘上刻上图像”，好有趣呢
And this model cost a whopping $279.99.
这个型号发布于2002-7-15
Internal versions cost less,
当年要卖279.99美元
but on average they were all more expensive than the other CD-RW options
内置版的要便宜些
when it released on July 15th, 2002.
不过他们都要比当时同类的CD刻录机要贵上不少
As if I really needed to say 2002, though.
好像我说发布年份有点啰嗦了
SuperBart：本世纪初，互联网第一次兴起，那时的东西都要留点互联网的痕迹
就跟八十年代的“靡靡之音”一样，一听就是那个时代的Disco/港台味道
I mean, just take one look at that '@' sign in the name there and, yeah, 2002 indeed.
是吧，你看看名称上的“@”标志，妥妥的时代印记:-P
Now overall, this really is just a CD-RW.
不过说到底，这就是个CD刻录光驱
注：CD-ROM (Read-Only Memory) 预先压制好的数据CD
.    CD-R (Recordable) 一次写入，永久读取，但无法更改
.  CD-RW (ReWritable) 可写，可读，可擦除后重新写
I mean, it had a lotta great features for its time,
当然，这个光驱有很多在当时看来有很多不错的特性
but of course the standout was the 'T@2ing' ability,
不过最具代表性的就是"T@2ing"科技了
which Yamaha hailed as the first CD-RW drive that could be used for on-disc labeling.
雅马哈声称这是第一个可以在CD数据面上刻上标签的刻录机
And it predates LightScribe by about two years.
这个技术也比LightScribe技术早了两年
There are some important distinctions between them, though,
当然，这两个技术之间还是有所区别的
because with LightScribe you had to have LightScribe media
你要使用LightScribe技术的话，你需要用专门
and it printed on the label side, as you'd expect.
为LightScribe设计的刻录盘，当然，这是印在标签面的
But with DiscT@2ing, it's on the data side of the disc where it puts the label,
不过使用DiscT@2ing技术的话，你就可以在数据面上刻标签了
which, yes, that means it limits your data storage capability on your CD-R.
不过，这样会减少你能在CD上刻录上的容量
But Yamaha claimed that most users
不过雅马哈说，大多数用户只会在光盘上刻录350MB的数据
only recorded about 350 megabytes onto CD-R anyway,
so it's fine, don't worry about it.
所以限制点就限制点吧:-P
They were happy to brag about all of its cool applications
雅马哈还在宣传物上大肆宣传
in its "Burnin' Love" press release, saying that you could write:
该技术的广泛用途，声称可以刻上
"Graphic images which are practically tattooed on,"
”你去纹身的时候纹上的图案“
SuperBart：所以纹身要纹上什么图案呢？
and, "This enables the user to write a practical memo
而且“这也允许用户在光盘的未使用区域刻上
such as a date, index, logo or picture on the unused area of the disc."
日期，索引，图标，或是图片”
And yeah, the other big distinction is that you can use any disc you want.
而且，还有一个区别，你可以在任意一张刻录CD上刻上图案
As long as it's a CD-R, DiscT@2ing works.
只要是刻录CD，DiscT@2ing就能用
Though Yamaha did sell their own DiscT@2 media as well with blue AZO dye.
不过雅马哈还是专门出品了为该特性设计的刻录盘
Eh, so that was a thing, but yeah, you can use whatever CD-Rs you want.
用的是蓝色AZO染料，当然，你也可以用自己的CD-R
注：刻录光盘的工作原理就是光盘上的染料受到激光影响而变化，进而产生“坑”
Now, the way this works, according to the old coverage that I found of this,
在我查阅了很多老资料后，我现在要介绍使用方法了
is that you make a disc design and then that is then turned by the software into a bitmap
你自己设计图案，然后程序将你的设计图案转换为位图
and converted from Cartesian to polar coordinates
并在将其写入刻录机的8MB缓存前，将直角坐标转变为极坐标
before being written to the CRW-F1's 8-megabyte cache.
And then the data is transferred sequentially
然后数据就从缓存按顺序传输到YDC132-V控制芯片
from the cache to the YDC132-V controller chip,
something Yamaha was very proud of, it was in all the marketing,
看上去雅马哈对这个芯片引以为傲，营销词上到处都有提到
and then it converts the greyscale information from the image into a pixel pattern
然后它将图案上的灰度值转换成像素元素
with a minimum pixel size, or pit size, of .1 millimeter.
内含一最小的像素大小，亦称坑大小，也就是0.1mm
And of course this also meant that the disc's
当然，这也意味着，光盘的目录必须在刻录图案前写入光盘
注：光盘的“目录”就是指光盘上数据区的位置，或是音轨的位置
而数据区前有lead-in，后有lead-out，相当于基因的启动子和终止子
table of contents had to be written before the label,
otherwise there'd be problems with drives
要不然，光驱就会尝试读取图案里的“坑”，误读取出数据
注：把光盘放大后，你会发现光盘上的数据就是通过有坑与没坑的状态存储的
trying to read the label with its tiny little pits as data
and then screwing things up, and you don't want that.
然后一切都变得混乱，你绝对不想看到吧:-P
And as soon as I heard about thing, the obvious question is,
我看完这些介绍后，就想：”到底最终会有怎样的效果呢？“
"What in the world are the results like?"
because Yamaha always showed these higher-contrast images
因为无论是在介绍资料，还是在广告啥的，雅马哈一直在展示
on blue CD-Rs and press releases and ads and whatnot
蓝色刻录CD的刻录成果，看上去对比度十分高
and it all seemed very controlled, made me a little skeptical.
看上去就像是都被控制好的，这让我更加怀疑了
SuperBart：实验室数据和现实效果的区别:-P
And the overall consensus from reviewers at the time
而当时的科技评论人一致认为
seems to be that DiscT@2ing was fun but not very useful.
这个东西虽然有趣，但难以实用化
It was praised largely for its other features.
不过这个光驱的其他特性是受到了广泛好评
You know, the drive itself.
It had very fast CD-RW writing,
它的刻录速度很快
a large eight-megabyte buffer,
内置8MB大缓存
and a whole buncha really cool audio recording stuff,
还有很多的关于刻录音频啥的
but it was deemed to not really be worth
不过相比同类产品，卖这么高的价格确实有点不值
the relatively high asking price compared to its competitors.
So most reviewers just said, "Wait for a sale."
所以评论界一致认为：“等促销再买吧。”
And, well, it didn't last very long.
然而，它在市场上没有存在很长时间
Yamaha actually stopped making the drives in 2003,
雅马哈早在2003年就停止生产这个产品了
so this barely lasted a year on the market
所以在官方砍掉这个产品前，他只在市场存在了
before having the plug pulled and DiscT@2ing was all but forgotten about,
大概一年吧，而且DiscT@2技术要不是这件事外
with a notable exception, because the tech kind of evolved
基本也要被大家遗忘了，由于技术的进步
and it eventually resulted in Labelflash in 2005,
DiscT@2技术在雅马哈和富士公司的合作下
which was a collaboration between Yamaha and Fujifilm.
在2005年进化为Labelflash技术
And while that was very similar
虽然这两个技术十分相似
in that you could print labels on the data side of your DVD,
都可以在数据区上刻录图案
it was only DVDs and not CDs
Labelflash技术只支持DVD，不支持CD
and it required a proprietary DVD-R media supporting Labelflash.
而且这个需要专门支持该技术的DVD-R
And even more similar than that was Lite-On's LabelTag,
还有一个相似的技术，就是Lite-On的LabelTag技术
although it's not really related as far as I can tell in terms of the tech.
尽管在技术层面，这和我今天要讲的东西没啥关系
That arrived in 2010 and it didn't need proprietary discs,
它发布于2010年，无需专门买盘即可刻录，和DiscT@2相似
much like DiscT@2, but again, it only worked on DVD recordable media, not CD-Rs.
但是，这个技术仍然仅支持DVD刻录盘，不支持CD刻录盘
Also of note is that despite the fact that DiscT@2 was dropped by Yamaha in 2003,
还有一件事，尽管DiscT@2技术在2003年被雅马哈抛弃
NEC and Pioneer also built drives with DiscT@2 support until 2010, technically.
NEC和先锋公司直到2010年仍在生产支持该技术的光驱
More so it was included by default because of the aforementioned Labelflash
而预置该功能的原因是前面提到的Lableflash
and Labelflash DVD burners retained DiscT@2 compatibility, just kind of as a given.
支持Laserflash的刻录机仍保留DiscT@2的兼容性，就这样
Now, like I said, there were multiple versions of this.
我之前说过，这类光驱有很多种不同的版本
This just happens to be the external SCSI version,
而这个正好是外置SCSI接口版的
but there was also an external USB 2.0 model, and a Firewire one
不过也有外置USB 2.0版的，还有火线版的
and internal drives fitting in 5.25" drive bays over IDE in either white or black.
也有内置版的，适配5.25寸软盘驱动器槽位，有黑白两种配色
And, you know, any of these drives would've been pretty awesome to have at the time,
当然，在那个年代家里趁一个这个
just even without the DiscT@2ing.
就算没有DiscT@2ing那个鸡肋技术，那也简直是不得了
It's other capabilities?
所以该光驱的其他特性呢？
That's not why it's on "Oddware" here,
好吧，那些可不是它能上“LGR志异”的原因
because, uh, the other stuff is pretty great, not odd at all.
因为，其他的功能都挺好的，没有那么怪异
It's got a lotta great specs. Which I'm not interested in!
它有好多有用的特性，这里我就不提了
We're just gonna take a look at the DiscT@2ing features here,
我们只关心它的 DiscT@2ing 特性
so let's get it unboxed and set up.
那么，咱赶紧拆包看看吧
So you can see from the package contents what was supposed to be in here originally,
这里有个目录，写着盒子里应该有什么东西
but unfortunately it's not quite complete in this case.
可惜里面的东西不太全
But that's fine, it's still got what we need,
不过没关系，该有的东西都有
including the AC adapter, 12-volt, 3-amp, 36 watts.
这是一个电源适配器，12V*3A=36W
And the software, which, really, this is all we need
然后这个软件盘也很重要
since we're using the Windows version here.
我们这里选用Windows版的
It also came with some Mac software with a different program for burning stuff, Toast 5.
这里也有一张Mac版的刻录软件光盘，里面是另一个刻录软件
And a quick start guide, also this is also for the Macintosh.
还有一个快速入门指南，这是Mac版的
There's no Windows one. It was lost by the previous owner.
可惜没有Windows版的，估计之前使用它的人给弄丢了吧
Yeah, and then you got the drive itself.
然后呢，就是刻录机本体了
And there we go.
就是这个了
Pretty standard-lookin' external CD-RW drive
这个光驱看上去中规中矩
with that nice Yamaha logo debossed into the top.
顶部有一个雅马哈标志的浮雕
Pretty groovy sides goin' on here.
侧面在当时听流行的
And around back, SCSI connections,
背面则有SCSI接口
including some termination points,
还有一些终结点啥的
RCA line out for CD audio,
CD音频输出用的莲花头
power switch and port, that kinda thing.
电源开关和接口啥的
But yeah, it's high time to get this plugged into a Windows XP PC
好的，现在我们来将这个光驱接到Windows XP电脑上
and try our hand at inking up some CD-Rs with DiscT@2 :-)
然后在光盘上刻些图案吧
All right, so I've got the Yamaha drive plugged in to the Windows XP PC going here,
好的，我已经把光驱接到电脑上了
and that goes straight into SCSI.
走的是SCSI接口
And in terms of setup it's incredibly simple.
设置光驱还挺简单的呢
I've already done it. It pretty much just does it itself.
我已经搞完了，基本上它自己就能处理一切
The Adaptec SCSI controller card that's in this system just goes ahead and finds it.
电脑里的SCSI控制卡直接就认出光驱了
And it's that right there, it sees it as a CRW-F1S.
就是这个，看上去是CRW-F1S
And at this point it just looks like any other CD-RW that you have on Windows XP.
目前它看上去就是个很普通的CD刻录机
So it is ready to go.
现在一切准备就绪
And in terms of the software, that's also a little simpler than I thought it might be.
而刻录软件方面呢，比我想的要简单
Yeah, that thing whirring to life has got some noise.
好吧，这个光驱十分的吵
Anyway, yeah, this is it.
无论如何，这就是软件安装界面了，十分普通
It's just a Nero 5 installation with regular versions of Nero and NCD packet writing,
安装的是Nero 5，有刻录软件和NCD刻录软件
so you just install it like you normally would Nero Burning ROM.
你直接安装就行了，就跟你平常安装Nero刻录软件一样
No special drivers or Yamaha software
除了这个软件，我们不需要再安装驱动或是
or anything outside of the actual burning software itself.
雅马哈定制软件啥的了
So we'll go ahead and grab ourselves a CD-R.
现在我们要拿出一张CD-R光盘了
I got a fresh pack here.
我这有一大摞全新的呢
'Bout ready to boot up some LimeWire and get us some music.
现在该去QQ旋风那里下载点小电影了
注：Limewire是一个流行的P2P软件，相当于该死的迅雷或伟大的eMule
No, don't do that.
算了吧，我可不想 律 师 函 警 告
SuperBart：江湖传说，有人在美国下载电影，然后被DMCA寄律师函了
That's a terrible idea these days.
这年头版权流氓太厉害
SuperBart：Bring Full Tom and Jerry Back in Bilibili
Their copyright are expired in China!
Actually, it was a terrible idea back in the day, too.
实际上，在当年也得长个心眼
Use virus scanners, folks.
小心电脑中毒！
Anyway, here once again it just shows up like a normal recordable CD drive in Windows XP,
无论如何，系统认出这是张很普通的CD-R了
but we're gonna go ahead and open Burning ROM.
现在，咱打开安装的刻录软件
And you might've seen really briefly there there's a little, slight different thing here.
也许你们之前注意到了，版本号和平常的有一丁点不同
"Version 5.5.8.19 Yamaha."
普通版本号后面有“雅马哈”字样
So this is actually a slightly modified or augmented version of Nero 5, which is great.
这个软件相比原来的Nero 5有略微魔改扩充，我觉得挺好的
I mean, honestly, I still use a later version of Nero for burning certain types of CDs,
我现在依然在使用新版的Nero来刻盘
so really familiar and awesome to use.
所以对我而言，这玩意界面熟悉，用起来很顺手
And everything looks the same
看起来都没什么区别
except for when you get to this Miscellaneous tab whenever you're burning something.
除非你在刻录时有特殊需求，需要点进“杂项”菜单
You have Burn DiscT@2 as an option.
而这里有DiscT@2选项
So if you do that and click Create, it'll open this T@2 Editor.
选上并点击“创建”后，你会看到图案编辑器
And this is where you take care of doin' T@2s.
这里你就可以设计刻在光盘上的图案了
And it works pretty much like any other editor I've ever used for creating disc labels.
这个见面很像我见过的其他光盘标签编辑器了
I don't know what I'm creating here.
我都不知道我在瞎画些什么
Let's put some text onto it.
要不我往上面写点字
So we have a Text Box tool. An Artistic Text tool?
这里有文本框工具，还有艺术字工具？
So, of course, we can change the size.
好吧，我们可以改字号
We can change the font to whatever.
也可以随便改字体
I mean, we can go with Comic Sans if we want.
好吧，咱调皮一回，用个Comic Sans吧
Got a couple of different text options.
针对字体，还有很多不同的选项
We got Read-only, which just makes it, so you can't edit the text,
比如只读，也就是设定完后，就不能编辑了
and then Bent, which changes it...
也可以弯曲，咱来看看啥效果
Let's see.
Yeah, it just sorta wraps around the CD.
哦，合着就是绕着光盘中心转啊
Then you can do that.
然后可以这么做
And, of course, you can add images, too.
当然，你也可以加些图片
So you do that there...
就放在这吧
There you go. Look, we got an image on our CD.
好的，看看啊，CD上有张图片诶
I don't know how that would look.
我不知道最终效果会怎样
I guess it's up to us to see.
兴许有一千个哈姆雷特吧
Let's go ahead and put some text on the disc.
现在我们该在光盘上刻些字了
And the Brush section.
这是涂刷工具
This is really just filling in the text here,
就是把文字给上色啊
so you can have different patterns.
你也可以填充些不同的样式
And then you can also change the color, which seems utterly pointless to me
也可以改变颜色，我觉得没有任何意义
since you're not gonna get any color on the CD itself.
毕竟刻在盘上的图案肯定没有颜色
This doesn't print in color.
刻录机可没法刻上颜色
It's just burning in an area of the disc,
它只能在盘上的特定区域刻上形状
so I don't know why...
真是理解不能
Let's get rid of the style, at least.
好吧，咱把样式给去掉吧
Let's just make it white. Yeah, there we go.
就用全白填充吧
So a nice, bold, Comic Sans, mm.
好极了，全白的Comic Sans字体，好好看哦:-P
With lines around it
绕中心的字，以及不知为何被拉来当背景的图片
and a weird picture in the background that doesn't make sense to put on a CD,
but let's do it anyway.
就这么刻了
So you can hit the preview and there's kinda what you might get.
你可以点下“预览”选项来看看最终成果
Yeah, okay. We'll see.
好吧，这挺好
And at this point it's just the same as burning any other disc, so,
到这里呢，就和刻录一张普通的CD没什么区别了
I don't know, we don't need to put much on here.
这个嘛，也许我们不需要在盘上刻上太多东西
Let's just put those pictures that we were looking through.
就把我看到的图片给刻上吧
Yeah.
好的，开始刻录了
Burning CDs.
Ah, I remember how exciting and yet nerve-wracking this used to be.
好吧，想起当年刻盘时，我又兴奋又紧张
It was the worst feeling ever getting 80% through
当进度达到80%，遇到了某种缓存或写入错误时，真是崩溃啊
and then you get some weird buffer or disc writing problem.
All right, and it burned our ridiculously tiny three-megabyte CD-ROM image here.
好的，超小的3MB的图像数据已经写入CD了
And now it switches over to this process:
现在正在切换至这个步骤
"Burning the bitmap to the disc."
“将位图刻进光盘”
So this takes a little while to do a whole CD's worth of T@2ing.
在整张CD上刻上图片确实费时
Yay. "Burning the bitmap completed successfully."
好的，“位图文件刻录完毕”
So let's see what we got.
看看成果吧
This is terrible!
效果真差:-(
You can't see the image beneath it, like, at all, can you?
你确实可以看到刻进去的图案......是吧？
I can't.
我是看不到
No? Okay, there's a tiny bit...
等会，这确实有一点......
Well, let me get another angle.
好吧，换个角度来看
Yeah, there's a little, tiny bit
好吧，这里确实有一点背景图片的山峦啥的
of that rocky formation coming through of the photo that we put in the background.
And you can see Comic Sans, just the text put on there,
还有那个我放上去的字
but if you didn't know there was supposed to be a label on there,
但是呢，如果没人告诉你这里有图片的话，你八成看不出来
you couldn't really tell.
I mean, from where I'm sitting, I can see the T@2 in there,
从我目前的位置来看，这里确实有点图案
just like a third of the disc at a time.
貌似在光盘的第三个数据区
But really, the thing that's even more obvious that I can see when putting it up to the light
不过，如果我把光盘放在强光下的话
is the label from other side shining through the CD-R.
那光盘标签面透过来的痕迹就更明显了
That's like 20 times more visible than the tattoo is.
我觉得比刻上去的图案还要清晰20倍
So I was looking through some old reviews about the DiscT@2ing system
我在搜集对DiscT@2ing系统的看法时
and that was one of the primary complaints.
我看到了很多对这种现象的抱怨
It was like you just can't see whatever you tattooed on the back of your CD,
在普通的，浅色染料制作的刻录CD上
on your typical CD-R, with a lighter greenish type of dye that's used.
你不能看到CD数据面上所有刻上去的图案
So what Yamaha recommended was to use CD-Rs that are a different color.
在这种情况下，雅马哈推荐使用另一种颜色的光盘
So one that I had on hand,
这个我倒是有
this right here is just a CD-RW from Maxell.
这是由Maxell生产的CD-RW盘
And you can see it's a lot darker,
这个的颜色更深
which should result in a darker, more bold T@2.
也许刻出来的图案颜色更深，更容易辨别
However, there's a problem.
不过，有一个问题
It throws up a warning that this CD is not a CD-R.
这玩意报错了，说这玩意不是CD-R
"DiscT@2s can only be printed on a CD-R.
"DiscT@2s 只能刻在CD-R上
The medium in your drive seems not to be a CD-R,
你放入的介质看上去不是CD-R
so please change it."
请换一个介质吧"
I'm not sure why that's a restriction, exactly, but it just sees it as not a CD-R,
我也不知道为啥会有这个限制，不过，看上去
so I can't use those.
只要不是CD-R,就用不了
So I went and ordered some of the ones that Yamaha actually seems to have recommended,
于是我去买了些雅马哈推荐的顶级刻录盘
these premium CD-Rs like the DataLifePlus here from Verbatim with AZO Blue technology.
诸如这个Verbatim生产的，使用了AZO蓝色染料
Better quality CD-Rs, something I never got back in the day
这种高品质的刻录盘，我那时买不起，因为太贵了
'cause they were just too expensive.
But they do have a notably darker tone to them.
不过数据面确实比通常的要深
I mean, look at that. Yeah, look at me.
来看看吧，顺便欣赏我帅气的脸:^)
So this should be pretty much the ideal DiscT@2 medium.
也许这才是最适合使用 DiscT@2 的光盘吧
So we're gonna try that and adjust the image just a little bit here
这里我用那张光盘，再稍微调整一下图片
to see if we can get a more bold, higher-contrasty look.
看看能不能得到一张更深，对比度更高的图片
Adjust the background a little bit here
调整一下图片，显得图片有点变化
to make it, yeah, not quite the same all the way around.
And I'm gonna go in the opposite direction with the color of the text.
这里我要将字上的颜色给改一下
Yeah, black with white around the edges.
没错，黑色填充，白色边框
We'll see if that works.
一会看看效果如何
All right, it sees that as a CD-R,
好的，认出这是张CD-R了，挺好
which it is, so good.
All right, and we'll let it do its thing here.
好的，就先让他刻着
I'll be back in about five or six minutes.
我先花6分钟听首King Crimson去
Okay, let's see what we got.
好的，看看成果
Oh, yeah. This is better.
好极了，效果好多了
Now that is a DiscT@2.
这才是DiscT@2的真实效果啊
A little more in line with what I was imagining slash hoping for.
文字更明显了，符合我的预期
Still not the most visible thing in the world,
然而还不是特别明显
but at least it's immediately obvious at a quick glance
不过至少让人能一眼看上去就知道上面有图案了
that it is supposed to be a label of sorts.
Making the text black certainly helped,
文字用黑色填充果然有用:-)
but, I mean, you can see even the white stroke around the text a lot more easily,
当然，文字周围的白色边框也能让文字更好认出了
and of course, you can actually make out some of the photo that's on there.
而且，你也能看出这上面刻有图片
I kinda see there, behind the O and the M, just little bits of rock formations.
在O和M之间有个图像，像是岩石纹理
Anyway, it's there. Again, you can only see it from certain angles,
好吧，你得倾斜一定角度才能看到盘上的部分纹理
and certain percentages of the disc at once,
but I can see probably half of the disc at once
不过我能一次性看到图片的一半到三分之二
as opposed to maybe just a third with the other one.
Yeah. I mean, look at that.
来看看，这根本没法对比啊
Just still a pretty lackluster result.
And being that we had to use one of the higher-quality,
要达到这种效果，你必须要用高质量的消费级CD刻录盘
consumer-grade CD recordable media.
In order to pull off even this meh kinda result,
then you can see why this didn't exactly set the world on fire
你也看到，何在数据面刻上图案的主意在当年没有那么流行
in terms of disc labeling options inside of CD recordable drives.
The thing is, though, this is all the unused space.
还有一件事，刻上图案的部分都是没使用过的
It's just that little ring, a tiny little bit in the middle there,
数据区就是中间的一个小环，也就几MB大小:-P
that it's actually using to store data, only a few megs.
So let's see what happens if we have basically the entire CD-R full of data.
现在来看看如果我在CD-R上充分刻上数据会有什么结果
And in order to test this, I figured I'd take the opportunity
为了测试，我要使用这些不同厂家生产的彩色CD刻录盘
to try one of these color CD-Rs that were sold by various companies back in the day.
I think these are from Memorex. Yeah.
这个应该是Memorex的吧
I don't know if the dye is any different
我不知道光盘上用的是啥染料，染料上有啥区别
or even what kinda dye is used inside,
but I know that the polycarbonate, at least,
至少我知道聚碳酸酯能让光盘上有色彩
is tinted in such a way that it's got a color to it.
Yeah. Memorex Cool Colors.
这就是 Memorex Cool Colors 了
So you got the regular label on that side and then the data side here has a hue added to it.
标签面比较普通，但是数据面则是上过色的
And to fill up a good chunk of the disc, we're gonna go meta here
为了在光盘上刻上大量数据，我给光盘取了个名字
and burn the "Oddware" episode that we're recording right now, or at least a chunk of it.
并将本期视频刻在光盘上，至少是一段片段
"And this is where you take care of doin' T@2s. And it works..."
"在这里你能设计你的刻盘图案了......"
Yeah, that's just weird. "Oddwareception."
真是怪异至极，在LGR志异中看LGR志异:-P
So this just goes into our ISO we just made here.
现在我要打开我刚制作的ISO文件了
Takes up about 500 megs of space,
占用大约500MB空间
leaving us this much to actually write our T@2 to the disc.
大致剩下这些空间来刻录我们的图案
And now, at this point,
现在我有点怀疑，会不会在编辑器里限制空间
I'm assuming it will cut down what we can actually do in the label creator...
Okay, I guess not.
然而并没有
Yeah, I got the CD-R in there.
好的，我把光盘放入了
I knows how big it is and how much space we're gonna be using,
我知道文件很大，要占用多大地方刻录
so I would assume that it would've automatically adjusted this.
我原先以为他会自动调整位置呢
I mean, we can do it manually.
当然，我们也能自己调整大小
You can see that shrinks down the radius.
我现在正在缩小半径呢
But, I don't know, let's just put something in there.
但也不知道对不对，先放些东西吧
Maybe it'll do it after the fact.
兴许回来能自动调整吧
Yeah, again, I don't know how much of this, we're actually gonna be able to use,
说真的，我不知道这到底要占多大地儿，不过希望光盘能用
so let's try it and we'll see what it does.
那么，咱们来试试，看最终如何吧
All right. Well, that answers that question.
好的，这解开了我的疑惑
"Warning! Your DiscT@2 does not fit on the CD.
"警告！你的图案无法与CD相适配
Do you want to open the thing and edit it to change the radii,
你是否想打开设置，重新调整直径
do you want to burn it partly on the remaining space,"
或是在空余位置刻录上部分图像？"
I guess it'll just crop it off,
我看就刻录一部分图像吧
"Or do you not want to write the T@2 anymore?"
"或是不再刻录图片了？"
Nah, we wanna write it, man.
不不，刻录是一定的!
Let's edit that thing down.
还是编辑一下吧
So I'm assuming this will now... It will.
我在想它会不会......是这样的
So that's how much of a radius we've got to work with.
好的，这就是调整半径之后的结果了
Okay. We have our adjusted label, or T@2.
这就是调整后的位图了
Can't imagine that'll end up taking too very long
想不到就在光盘最外层刻上那么一小圈，也是那么的耗时
considering it's only a sliver around the edge of the CD-R that we're T@2ing.
Yep, it's finishing up
好的，花了不到3分钟就刻完了，大约是两分半
and it didn't even take three minutes.
About two and half minutes to do that.
Let's see what we got.
看看成果吧
Oh-ho-ho no!
X﹏X
Oh, it's even worse than that first CD-R.
甚至比第一张还差:-(
You can't see anything!
你嘛也看不见！
Like, if you look right about here, you can see the word...
你看啊，就这边缘位置，你可以大致看到些文字
"This is a smaller DiscT@2."
“这是个更小的DiscT@2”
That's it. So much for Cool Colors.
就这样，这张盘就说到这
The colors might be cool,
颜色也许挺酷的
but the DiscT@2ing potential is not.
但是刻上去的图案太浅了，不太好
Again, compared to the blue AZO dye version,
再看看这个蓝色AZO染料的光盘
yeah, you can see why Yamaha recommended this and sold their own DiscT@2...
你就明白为啥雅马哈推荐这种盘，并售卖自己的DiscT@2光盘
Oh, see? That's about the best angle of it right there.
再看看，这是观看刻上图片的最佳形式
See that? That's ideal.
这可真是理想状态哦
But that's not how it looks in real life.
不过这可不是现实中看到的样子
This is just a reflection that you're seeing directly from the overhead light in the camera.
这个只是照相机拍到的顶灯反射在光盘上的样子
Anyway. That's the DiscT@2.
好的，这就是DiscT@2了
Yeah. Well, this has certainly been an experience.
好的，这就是我体验这个光驱的过程了
The CRW-F1, a great CD-RW for the time,
这台 CRW-F1 ，当时最好的光驱之一
and honestly it's still pretty good despite the SCSI connection kinda limiting things.
尽管使用的是落后的SCSI接口，搁现在也是好玩意啊
But, you know, the DiscT@2ing gimmick, it's...
不过，DiscT@2这个小花活呢，基本没啥用
It's a gimmick. It's not the most useful thing.
You can totally see where they were coming from in the old reviews, where, you know,
你可以从某些老物件回顾纪录片中看到这玩意的来龙去脉
I mean this right here, look at that. There's not much to it.
但你看这成果，真的是难堪大用啊
You can barely see that anything is there on your standard type of CD-R material
你很难从当时流行的普通CD-R上看到你刻上去的图案啊
and dyes that were used most often.
Even when you go to the expensive stuff that Yamaha recommended, that's as good as it got.
如果你用了雅马哈推荐的昂贵刻录盘的话，效果倒是还行
So, ya know. DiscT@2ing. I'd be curious if any of you actually used this.
好吧，就这玩意，我有点怀疑观众朋友们到底有没有用过:-P
I mean, I know I certainly used things like LightScribe later on,
当然，我之后是用过LightScribe，但这俩可不是一类东西啊
but this is a whole different thing.
And the fact that it takes up so much of the data side,
而且还在数据区上浪费那么多的空间，毫无意义
it's just silly and it's prime "Oddware," and I hope that you enjoyed seeing it.
值得被列入我的"志异"系列，希望大家"看得"愉快
...Just, seeing it.
......看视频愉快啦
本片由SuperBart翻译,原作者LGR上传于2021年3月5日
字幕下载：github.com/BenderBolg/Subtitles
支持原作者：patreon.com/LazyGameReviews​
And if you did like seeing it, then let me know it in the comments.
如果你们喜欢看的话，到原作者和翻译的评论区下留言吧
And do check out other "Oddware" episodes if you like this kinda thing,
去看看翻译的"LGR志异"收藏夹吧
搬运来的LGR Oddware熟肉基本都在了
or stick around for other new LGR things each week here on this channel.
或者关注原作者的Youtube，每周都有更新的
And as always, thanks for watching!
最后，一如既往，感谢大家收看:^)